I'm here today to talk
about thinking for yourself.
And I must admit, I did use AI
to help me think about it.
(Laughter)
The irony is not lost on me.
But the way I did so
is not by using AI as an assistant
to help me prepare this talk faster.
Rather, I use AI as a tool for thought.
And by the end of this talk,
I will have explained what I mean by that,
why it's important,
and given you a glimpse
of how it might work.
But first I need to set the scene.
Let's look at a day in the life
of a 21st-century knowledge worker.
I arrive at my office and look
at my inbox full of emails.
Oh.
Let's summarize it.
OK, I'm struggling to figure out
how to respond here,
so let's get AI to write a response.
Next, I need to write a report.
But I'm struck by the blank-page problem.
I know, I'll drop in some resources
and get an AI draft.
Looks good to me.
By the way, a writer's block
used to be staring at a blank page.
Now it's staring at a page
that AI filled out for me
and wondering if I agree with it.
I've become a professional
validator of a robot's opinions.
(Laughter)
I've got some data to analyze.
Maybe AI can analyze this data for me.
Probably correct.
OK, I've got to make a deck as well.
You know the drill.
Alright.
Oh, I was supposed
to prototype something as well.
OK, let me vibe code something.
Alright, all this looks good, let's go.
This isn't a vision of the future.
This is a completely plausible,
if slightly exaggerated, picture
of the world of knowledge work today.
Welcome to the age of outsourced reason.
Where the knowledge worker no longer
engages with the materials of their craft.
We've become intellectual tourists.
In our own work, we visit ideas.
We don't inhabit them.
Our relationship to our work
is entirely intermediated by AI.
Some might say alienated.
We've heard that story before.
What's wrong with this picture?
For one thing, it's only
one step removed from this,
which is important.
But that's a different talk.
What I want to focus on today
is that using AI in this way
can have profound implications
on human thought.
Consider creativity.
On an individual level,
we might think that AI
is a creativity boost,
giving us rapid access to new ideas.
But numerous studies have shown
that on a collective level,
knowledge workers using AI assistants
produce a smaller range of ideas
than a group working manually.
We've created a hive mind.
Except the hive is really boring
and keeps suggesting the same five ideas.
Consider critical thinking.
We surveyed knowledge workers
about their use of AI.
They reported that they put less effort
into critical thinking
when working with AI
than when working manually.
And this effect was greater
when they had greater confidence in AI
and less confidence in themselves.
Consider memory.
When people rely on AI to write for them,
they remember less of what they wrote.
And when they read AI-generated summaries,
it's hardly surprising
that they remember less
than if they'd read the document.
And finally, consider metacognition,
which is the ability to think
about your own thinking process.
Working with AI requires
significant metacognitive reasoning
about your task goals,
decomposing the task,
the applicability of gen-AI,
your ability to evaluate the output.
These are things which are built
into the process
of working directly with the material,
and which become problematic
when that material engagement
becomes intermediated.
Basically, we've become middle managers
for our own thoughts.
So what's the score?
We have fewer ideas.
We think about them less critically.
We remember them less well,
and we have a harder time doing it.
Taken together, we can see
that AI-assisted workflows
can have profound effects
on human thinking.
And this extends even to seemingly
trivial mundane tasks,
because these everyday opportunities
for exercising our creativity,
our critical thinking and our memory
are essential for protecting
our cognitive musculature
and allow us to rise to the occasion
when an exceptionally
complex task comes our way.
Studies show that when
we don't use our brains,
they get worse at brain things.
Nobel Prize committee,
please hold your applause.
Is this the cost of progress?
We've solved the problem
of having to think.
Unfortunately, thinking
wasn't actually a problem.
(Laughter)
It's like we invented a cure for exercise
and then wondered why
we're out of breath all the time,
you know?
It doesn't have to be this way.
Beyond AI as an assistant,
I believe that AI should be
a tool for thought.
AI should challenge, not obey.
And I believe that right at this moment,
we are at a critical juncture
where the world of work is poised
to be transformed by generative AI,
and we must act now
to shape and drive that transformation
towards humanistic values.
Of these two diverging roads,
we must take the one less traveled.
Beyond getting the job done,
a tool for thought helps us
better understand the job.
Beyond getting it done faster,
it helps us get it done better.
Beyond getting us to the right answers,
a tool for thought helps us
ask the right questions.
Beyond automating known processes,
it helps us explore the unknown.
What does this look like?
What I'm about to show you is a prototype,
developed by my colleagues and me
at the Tools for Thought team
at Microsoft Research in Cambridge.
Now, please bear in mind
that this is a live research prototype.
It's not a product.
And it's just one
of a series of explorations
that our team is conducting
to study how different modes
of working with AI
can enhance human thought.
So let's look at a fictitious example.
Clara and her colleagues run a company
that sells bottled beverages.
They've just had a meeting
to discuss a new industry report
that seems to have
some pretty important findings
about consumer preferences
for sustainable packaging.
Clara's colleagues have asked her
to write a proposal
arguing for how the company
ought to respond.
So she really needs
to get to grips with this proposal --
She really needs to get
to grips with this report,
understand its findings and its data
and how it fits into her business context.
She starts by loading some documents
into her workspace.
There's the meeting transcript
to remind her what was discussed.
There's a recent internal report
from her own business.
And of course,
there’s the industry
report, which she opens.
She sees an overview of the document
along with section-by-section summaries.
Except these aren't really just summaries.
We think of them more as lenses.
They're customizable
micro representations of the text
that can emphasize what is most relevant
to the task at hand.
So in this case, Clara selects
the consumer’s lens.
She can select a section
for deeper reading,
in this case the first one.
As she reads, she makes
notes about her thoughts
and highlights excerpts from the document.
As she reads,
she also sees AI-generated
commentary and critiques.
We call these provocations.
Here's a provocation that raises
a potential opportunity,
which she highlights and annotates.
Note how this process is a hybrid
of completely manual reading
and completely relying
on AI to read for you.
Clara still reads,
but intentionally and strategically.
Now, as Clara is working,
she's building up an outline
of her argument manually
in this pane on the right.
This outline is lightly structured
and allows her to sketch out the flow
of her argument at a high level,
while still retaining deep connections
and being grounded
in the source documents.
As a result of which we can already
generate a draft of the proposal,
and Clara can do things here
like add a heading to the outline
to generate a paragraph.
But what I want to draw
your attention to here
is that while this text is AI-generated,
Clara has a completely different
relationship to this text
than if she just dropped in some documents
and said, write me a report.
Because this text is deeply
rooted in a cognitively effortful
but interactionaly effortless
thought process.
It reflects Clara’s decisions,
Clara’s judgments,
Clara’s unique personal,
professional expertise.
She sees another provocation,
this time in the outline.
In this case, she decides
that while the provocation is useful,
she does not need to address it.
Unlike typical AI suggestions,
provocations are not meant
to be applicable all the time.
They're instead meant to stimulate
your thinking about your work.
Because if you understand
your work well enough,
deeply enough to make
the confident decision
not to accept a piece of feedback,
then the feedback process
is still working as intended.
But we're not done yet.
Clara has entirely new ways
of interacting with this text
because of generative AI.
A really simple example
is that she can just resize a paragraph
to change its length.
She can also rapidly test
different versions of this text.
For instance, in this paragraph,
she's wondering whether
it would be more effective
if it took a more inspirational
or more practical tone.
So she selects one
of these customizable dimensions.
And previews a few alternatives
and selects one.
And at select strategic points,
indeed, she writes.
As she writes, she sees provocations that,
rather than autocompleting her ideas,
they raise alternatives,
they identify fallacies,
they offer counterarguments
to help her strengthen
and develop her own argument.
There's something you won't find
anywhere in this interface.
And that's a chat box.
Clara’s not having to chat
with anything to do her work,
yet she is silently and appropriately
assisted by her computer
as a computer
and not as an ersatz human.
To put it simply,
we have gone from this ...
To this.
Throughout this process,
Clara has been assisted and yes,
probably worked faster because of AI.
But she's also maintained direct
material engagement at strategic points.
She read the relevant portions
of the document herself.
She constructed her decisions
on her argument herself.
And ultimately it can be said
she has written this document herself.
Moreover, she worked better because of AI.
AI provocations at every
stage of the process
kept her metacognitively engaged,
always looking for critiques,
alternatives and lateral moves.
We have been studying
the effects of tools like this.
And the results are promising.
You can demonstrably
reintroduce critical thinking
into AI-assisted work flows.
You can reverse the loss of creativity
and enhance it instead.
You can build powerful tools for memory
that enable knowledge workers
to read and write at speed
with greater intentionality,
and remember it, too.
It turns out, with the right
principles of design,
you can build tools
that are the best of both worlds.
Applying the awesome speed
and flexibility of this technology
to protect and enhance human thought.
These are simple, general principles,
like ensuring that the tool
preserves material engagement,
offers productive resistance,
and scaffolds metacognition.
And while we've been primarily studying
professional knowledge workers,
we believe that these principles
can extend to all aspects of AI use,
including when we use it
in our daily lives, our hobbies,
and even in education.
I repeat, efficiency is not the aim
of Tools for Thought.
Better thinking is.
But sometimes you can have both.
I used to think there was no such thing
as a free lunch in human thinking.
This is so much better than a free lunch.
This is a lunch that pays you to eat it.
(Laughter)
I want to close with some thoughts
on the values that we have
in developing AI software.
What if AI gets to the point
where it can do a better job
of thinking than humans?
Why should we care so much
about protecting
and augmenting human thought?
There's two reasons.
First,
there may always be ways of thinking
that remain unique human strengths
of which we may not even be aware.
Second, perhaps more importantly,
we take the position
that the ability to think well
is essential for human agency
and empowerment and flourishing.
This echoes an ancient question.
People once asked
if writing, if books, if the internet
can remember for us,
does it matter that we cannot?
People once asked if maps
can navigate for us,
does it matter that we cannot?
Now we ask if machines can think for us,
If machines can speak for us,
grieve for us, pray for us, love for us,
does it matter that we cannot?
To me, the answer is pretty obvious.
When I began studying human-AI
interaction 13 years ago,
it was inconceivable to me
that we would be asking
these questions in my lifetime.
But we are.
And we must.
I'll leave you with this thought.
What would you rather have?
A tool that thinks for you,
or a tool that makes you think?
(Applause)